A Guide to the Papers of K. Edward Lay
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Dwellings-Albemarle County and Charlottesville
  - Enniscorthy 2, Green Mountain, ca. 1784, burned 1839 1967-1999 (Box 7)
  - Enniscorthy 3, Green Mountain, 1850 1915-2000 (Box 7)
  - Ernscliffe, Simeon, Albemarle, 1850s, razed 1991 1977-1993 (Box 7)
  - Esmont, Esmont, ca. 1819, ca. 1953 1970-1990 (Box 7)
  - Estes (Ned) Farm (Fairview, Dover-Foxcroft), Earlysville, ca. 1812, 1910 1989 (Box 7)
  - Estouteville (Calycanthus Hill), Keene, ca. 1800, 1827-1830, 1983 1977-1991 (Box 7)
  - Everett House, Charlottesville (relocated from Milton), early 19th century 1965-1995 (Box 8)
  - Evergreen, Albemarle 1995 (Box 8)
  - "E" General 1978-1995 (Box 8)
    Eaglehurst Farm, Albemarle; Early House, Earlysville, late 19th century; 310 East Beverly Street, Staunton, 1845; Echo Hill, Farmington area; Eddins-Robinson House, Charlottesville, 1895; Eddins-Tilden House, Charlottesville, 1901; Edgewood, Charlottesville, 1889; Edgewood Farm, Albemarle, 1878; Egern, Carters Bridge Neighborhood, 1949; Ellen Spring Farm, Cismont/Keswick Hunt; M. C. Elliott House, Charlottesville, 1935; 801 Elliott Avenue, Charlottesville, 1925; Eltham Manor, Piedmont Country, Henry County, 1936; Elwyn Farm, Augusta County, 1747, 1830; Emergency Relocation Home, 9th S. W., 1886; Epilogue, Greenwood, Albemarle County, 1971; Esmont home, Albemarle; Estes (Algretous) Farm, Earlysville, 1901; Estes Farm, Albemarle, 1890s; G. T. Estes Farm, Free Union, 1902; R. N. Estes House, Earlysville, 1890s; Eubank Place, Carters Bridge, ca. 1800; Evans Log House, Crozet, 19th century, demolished ca. 1960
  - Fairmount, (Fairmont), Stony Point, ca. 1840, 1946 1957-1976 (Box 8)
  - Fairview Farm, (John L Manahan; John E. Manahan; Thomas Staples Martin House 1942), Scottsville, burned 1926, 1941 1987-1990 (Box 8)
  - Fairway, Farmington Country Club, 1930, 1950 1970 (Box 8)
  - Farm, The New, (built for John A. G. Davis; Thomas Farish Home), Charlottesville, 1826, brick addition 1850 1975-1999 (Box 8)
  - Farm, The Old, (built for Nicholas Lewis), Charlottesville, ca. 1770, 1939, 1949-1950 1987-2000 (Box 8)
  - Farmington, (Farmington Country Club 1929; Francis Jerdone Tory Home; Warner Wood Home; General Peyton Home), Farmington, 18th century, 1803, 1898, 1929 1967-1998 (Box 8)
  - Farmington Houses (unnamed), 20th century 1941-1997 (Box 8)
  - Faulkner House, (Old Ivy Inn - Seymour Montesano; McFarland Home; Louis T. Hanckel Home; Thomas S. Martin Home, Frizell Home; Charles Goodyear Home; Haze Home; Jewry/Jury Home), Albemarle, 1855-1856, 1907, 1991 1975-1996 (Box 8)
  - Feathers, Carters Bridge, (Featheridge; Belvidere; Falrose; Martin House), ca. 1800, 1820, 1939, 1960s 1975-1994 (Box 8)
  - Fielding, Ivy, ca. 1825-1840 1976-1991 (Box 8)
  - Fieldstone, Farmington, 1933 n.d. (Box 8)
  - Finally, (Wheeler Home), late 18th century, 1952 1991-1995 (Box 8)
  - Findowrie, Cismont, (Aspen Grove; Campbells), ca. 1733 1978-1995 (Box 8)
  - Fitch-Gleason House, Charlottesville, ca. 1845, ca. 1881 n.d. (Box 8)
  - Flordon, (Stone Hunting Lodge; James Camp Home), near Farmington, early 1930s 1983-1995 (Box 8)
  - Forest Hill Plantation, Simeon, (Poplar Forest; John Watson Home; Tandy Wilhoit Home), 1786, ca. 1802, ca. 1900, 1933, 1946 n.d. (Box 8)
  - Forest Lodge, Albemarle, ca. 1910, ca. 1941 n.d. (Box 8)
  - Foster House, (Catherine "Kitty" Foster), Charlottesville, ca. 1833 1993-1995 (Box 9)
  - Foster (Simon F.) House, Albemarle 1991 (Box 9)
  - Fosteria, (W. W. McClung Home), Batesville, ca. 1820 1991 (Box 9)
  - Four Acres, Charlottesville, 1910, ca. 1988 1979-1999 (Box 9)
  - Fowler House, (Parrott Cottage), Charlottesville, 1863, 1870s, 1923 1982-1995 (Box 9)
  - Fox Ridge Farm, Farmington Hunt, ca. 1850, 1941 1985-1988 (Box 9)
  - Franklin, Stony Point, Albemarle, ca. 1795 1988-1992 (Box 9)
  - Franklin-Halifax House, Free Union, 18th century n.d. (Box 9)
  - Fray, (Holly Tree Farm), Advance Mills, 1820s, mid 19th century 1995 (Box 9)
  - "F" General 1980-1995 (Box 9)
    Fairview Farm, Farmington Hunt; Fansler House, Charlottesville, 1888, ca. 1914, ca. 1929, 1979; G. W. Farish House, Charlottesville, 1870; Farm estates, Keswick; Faulconer Home, Farmington, 1931; Ferguson House, Farmington Hunt/Free Union, ca. 1790; Ficklin-Crawford Cottage, Charlottesville, 1870s-1886; Fiddler's Green, Albemarle, 20th century; Fife-Lupton Cottage, Charlottesville, 1891; Fifth Street House, Charlottesville; Finch-McGee House (Cottage), Charlottesville, 1884; Fiske (Barbara J.), Covesville, 1880; Five Oaks, Albemarle, 19th century; Five Oaks, Ivy, 1908; Five Oaks, Esmont, late 19th/early 20th century; Fleischman House, Crozet, 1890; Forest Oaks, Natural Bridge, ca. 1806; Foster Home, (Cocke-Foster House), Albemarle, 1865-1870, 1874; Foster-Critzer House, Batesville, late 19th century/20th century; Fox Ridge Farm, Albemarle, early 1800s; Foxden Farm, Shadwell, Keswick Hunt; Foxhaven, Albemarle, ca. 1937; Free Union Horse Farm, Free Union, ca. 1900; Fuller-Bailey House, Charlottesville, 1892; Fuller-Bailey House, Charlottesville, 1892
  - Gale Hill, (William Cecil Dabney Home), Albemarle, 1770, 1887, burned 1932 1993 (Box 9)
  - Gallison Hall, Farmington, 1931-1933 1969-1997 (Box 9)
  - Gardner House, Charlottesville, 1925 1993-1994 (Box 9)
  - Gentry House, Crozet, ca. 1825 1976 (Box 9)
  - George House, Charlottesville, ca. 1872 1980 (Box 9)
  - George House, (H.A. George, Jr. Home), Farmington, 1936, 1947 n.d. (Box 9)
  - Gianniny-Bailey House, Charlottesville, 1895 1995 (Box 9)
  - Gilmer-Wood House, Charlottesville, ca. 1820, razed pre-1901 n.d. (Box 9)
  - Gleason-Donovan House, Charlottesville, 1893 1995 (Box 9)
  - Glen Dower 1, (Claim House), Keene, ca. 1745-1760 1957-1995 (Box 9)
  - Glen Dower 2, (Scotts Mill; Dyers Mill), Keene, 1810, 19th century 1967-1995 (Box 9)
  - Glen Echo, Albemarle, ca. 1760, 1936, ca. 1941 1977-1987 (Box 9)
  - Glen Esk, (Marshall Durrett Place), North Garden, ca. 1790-1803 1980-1997 (Box 9)
  - Glenmore, (Thomas Esten Randolph Home; Louis H. Girardin Home; Walker Timberlake Home; Thomas G. Watkins Home; Benjamin Henry Magruder Home); Shadwell, 1795, 1843 1957-1997 (Box 9)
  - Glentivar, Greenwood, early 19th century, mid 19th century, 1989 1993-1998 (Box 9)
  - Goodwin Farm, Camp Holiday Trails, Albemarle, 1820s n.d. (Box 9)
  - Gorman House, Charlottesville, 1825 1993 (Box 9)
  - Grassmere, Ivy, ca. 1830, ca. 1860 1976-1990 (Box 9)
  - Greenfields, Scottsville, 1904 1977-1995 (Box 9)
  - Greenwood Farm, (William Dinwiddie Home), Albemarle, ca. 1915 n.d. (Box 9)
  - Guthrie Hall, Green Mountain, ca. 1901-1905 1978-1997 (Box 9)
  - "G" General 1981-1995 (Box 10)
    Gaar-Madison, Free Union, ca. 1740, ca. 1840; Gamble-McCullough House, Charlottesville, 1890; Gardner-Mays Cottage, Earlysville, 1891; Garland Property, Albemarle, 1969-1970; Garnett House, Earlysville, mid 19th century; Gee House, Charlottesville, 1920s; Geiger-Coles House, Charlottesville, 1881; H. H. George House, Charlottesville, 1889-1891; George-Makris House, Charlottesville, 1882-1889; George-Perry House, Charlottesville, 1889-1891; Gibson Houses, Estes Street, Charlottesville, 1900; Giddings, 1930s, razed; Gillespie-Wright House, Charlottesville, 1887; Gilmore-Watts House, Charlottesville, 1922; Gilmorton, ca.1816
    H. M. Gleason House, Charlottesville, ca. 1881, 1906; Gleason-Pendleton House, Charlottesville, ca. 1889; Glen Arvon, Albemarle, 1830; Glenmore Farm, Amelia County, 18th century; Glenwood, ca. 1847; Gloeckner House, Charlottesville, 1900; Goins (Robert) House, Charlottesville, ca. 1845-1849, ca. 1870-1875, 1957, 1964; Goldsmith House, Charlottesville, 1882-1889; Gooch House (W. D. Dabney Home), Charlottesville, ca.1870; Goodwin House, (Bemiss House), 1930s, 1992 addition; Gracroft, Albemarle; Graecote, Albemarle, 1962
    Grassmere, Ivy, 20th century; 708 Graves Street, Charlottesville, 1918, 1993; Grayson, Keene, 1924-1927; Graystone, Farmington, 20th century; Green Creek farm estates, Albemarle, ca.1910; Green House, Batesville, mid 19th century; Greene Mount, King and Queen County, ca. 1770; Green Mountain, Boonesville, ca. 1802; Green Pastures, Albemarle County; Green Plains, Albemarle, 1836; Greenhills, Albemarle, ca. 1970; Greenway Farm, Greenwood, 19th century; remodeled 1970; Greenwood Cottage, Greenwood, Grigg (Milton L.) House, Charlottesville, 1948; The Grove, (Barksdale-Totty House), Charlottesville, 19th century; Grove Hill Farm, Albemarle, 1937, 1947
  - Haden-Coles House, (Elizabeth Coles Home), Charlottesville, 1915-1918, razed 1980-1995 (Box 10)
  - Hale House, (William Newton Hale), Charlottesville, 1949 1985 (Box 10)
  - Hampstead, (Belle Gate; Rin Ran), Albemarle, dated timber 1804, 1830s, mid 20th century 1978-1995 (Box 10)
  - Hanckel House, (Lewis Hackel Home), Charlottesville, early 19th century 1995 (Box 10)
  - Hard Bargain, Charlottesville, 1878 1978 (Box 10)
  - Harris Houses, (Harris Farm Slave House, Albemarle, ca. 1840-1860; Harris House outbuilding, Free Union, late 19th early 20th century) 1980-1990 (Box 10)
  - Harris-Sheperd House, Charlottesville, 1905, razed ca. 1981 1980 (Box 10)
  - Hatton Grange, (Mountain View), Albemarle, 1831, 1898 1991-1996 (Box 10)
  - Hatton on the James, Albemarle, early-mid 19th century 1996 (Box 10)
  - Hawkins-Wondree House, Charlottesville, ca. 1835, 1892 1977 (Box 10)
  - Head of Creek Plantation, (Woodlawn Farm; The Willows; Old Plantation; Edward Garland Home; Joseph Sutherland Home), ca. 1790, burned ca. 1970 1980-1995 (Box 10)
  - Headquarters, (Mountain View; Bruce House), Browns Cove, 1769, frame burned, 1812 rear, 1818 brick, 1956 1954-1991 (Box 10)
  - Heiskell-Livers Townhouse 1, (John L. Livers Home 1913), Charlottesville, ca. 1822, 1915 1975-1994 (Box 10)
  - Heiskell-Livers Townhouse 2, (McKennie-Livers Annex), Charlottesville, 1842 1995 (Box 10)
  - Hermitage. Albemarle 1982-1991 (Box 10)
  - Hessian Road house, Charlottesville, 20th century 1994 (Box 10)
  - Hidden Acres, Albemarle, 1850-1870, 1930s 1976 (Box 10)
  - High Meadows, (Fairview; Mountain Sunset), Scottsville, 1832, 1883 1986-1995 (Box 10)
  - High Mowing, (Sally Alexander Martin Home), Albemarle, 1856, 1862 1991-1995 (Box 10)
  - High Oaks, Farmington, ca. 1938 1977 (Box 10)
  - Highlands, (Magnolia Cottage), Albemarle, 1929, 1936, 1938 n.d. (Box 10)
  - Hill, The, (John W. Davis Home; Thomas Walker Gilmer Home; T. J. Williams Home; C. H. Walker Home; John T. Antrim, Sr. Home), Charlottesville, 1831, razed 1904 1991 (Box 10)
  - Hill House, Batesville, late 19th century, 1979 1988-1993 (Box 10)
  - Hill House (William Maury Hill House), (other owners include James Dinsmore, John A. G. Davis, John Smith. Benjamin P. A. Warthen), Dudley Mountain, 19th century 1991-1998 (Box 10)
  - Hill Top, (Charles R. Dorrier House), Scottsville, ca. 1914 1976-1991 (Box 10)
  - Hillcrest Farm, (Verdant Lawn; High Ground; John T. Randolph Home; Paul B. Barringer Sanitorium; Percy Brown Home; Tandem School), Albemarle, ca. 1840 1991-1997 (Box 10)
  - Hillside, (Harmon House), Charlottesville, 1899 1996 (Box 10)
  - Hodges-Gleason House, (Barksdale House), Charlottesville, 1857 1974-1995 (Box 10)
  - Holly Croft, (Tuckedin), Keswick, ca. 1860, 1970 1986 (Box 10)
  - Holly Fork, (Hopewell; Hopedale), Cismont, late 18th century, burned 1849 & 1966 1957-1978 (Box 10)
  - Holly Hollow, (Daniel Wood House), Ivy, 1837 1976-1998 (Box 10)
  - Holly Tree Farm, Advance Mills, ca. 1790 1994 (Box 10)
  - Hollymead, (Dean Runk Home; Silver Thatch Inn), Albemarle, ca. 1777, ca. 1800, 1936-1937, 1963 1973-1995 (Box 10)
  - Home Tract, (Hughes House; White House), Ivy, 1803, 1812, 1870, ca. 1925 1976-1999 (Box 10)
  - Homeplace, The, (William Tompkins Home; White Hall), White Hall, mid 19th century, 1975 1976-1979 (Box 10)
  - Horseshoe, The, Woodsons Corner, mid 19th century, mid 20th century 1991-1995 (Box 10)
  - Horseshoe Retreat, (Gay House; Old James C. Houchens Home), Gay Mountain, mid 19th century, 1951-1952 1993 (Box 10)
  - Hotopp-Watson House, Charlottesville, 1900 n.d. (Box 10)
  - House at Lindsay, mid 19th century n.d. (Box 10)
  - Houses, (various unnamed houses), Charlottesville and Albemarle 1995-1998 (Box 10)
  - Howard House, (Lucy Howard House razed), Israels Gap, ca. 1900 1991-1995 (Box 11)
  - Howardsville Tripartite House, ca. 1830, ruins from 1969 flood 1976-1995 (Box 11)
  - Howardsville (various unnamed houses), ca. 1800, 1846, 1880s 1974-1989 (Box 11)
  - Hughes House, Charlottesville, ca. 1853 n.d. (Box 11)
  - Hulfish House, Charlottesville, 1902, 1987 n.d. (Box 11)
  - Hydraulic Mills, (Redbrook; Running Fox); ca. 1818, 1829, 1939 1976 (Box 11)
  - "H" General 1956-1996 (Box 11)
    Halcyon, Albemarle; Hale House, (Holmes House), Hessian Road, ca. 1948; Hale House, Meadowbrook Road, 1949; Halfway House, Farmington, 20th century; Halifax House, Albemarle, 19th century, mid 20th century; Hall Place, Albemarle, 1830; Hammond House, Charlottesville, 1925; Hancock House, Charlottesville, 1874; Hannah House, Crozet, 1900; Hansen House, Pantops Mountain, 1940s; Harris House, Albemarle, late 19th century; Harris House, (Davis House), White Hall, late 18th century; Harrison House, Albemarle, mid 19th century; Harrison House, (W. Wright Harrison House), Farmington, 20th century; Hart House, Albemarle, ante 1820, 1870s; Hartnagle-Witt House, Charlottesville, 1884; Hatch House, (Rev. J. W. Hatch House; Dr. W. D. Macon House), Charlottesville; Hawkins-Harmon House, (Pace's Taxi Co., Inc.), Charlottesville, ca. 1843; Hawkins-Holmes House, (John A. Holmes Home; William Dyer Wheeler Home), Charlottesville, 1850s; Hawkins-Perry House, Charlottesville, 1873
    Hearthwood House, Ivy, ca. 1881; Heathcote, Keswick Hunt, ca. 1915; Heatwole, Charlottesville, 1920; Hectic Hill, Albemarle, ca. 1792; The Hedges, (Happy Creek), Albemarle, 20th century; Heiskell House, (John J. Collier, J. Henry Irving owners), Charlottesville, ca. 1822, razed; Henderson House, Charlottesville, 1934; Herndon House, (Parr Home; Andy Johnson Home), Scottsville, ca. 1810; Herring-Turner House, Charlottesville, 1914; Highlands, Farmington Hunt, 20th century; Hillcrest Apartments Cottage, Charlottesville, 19th century, moved ca. 1892; Hill-Holladay House, Charlottesville, 1905; Hillel Foundation, Charlottesville, ca. 1913-1914; Hilltop, Esmont
    Holladay House, Charlottesville, 1894; Historic Downtown House, late 19th century; Hollow Tree, (Greenway), Green Mountain, 1893, 1920s; Holly Hill, (Martin-Wilder House), Charlottesville, 1899; Holly Hill, (Major Henry Wise guest house), Farmington, 1957; Holt Farm, Keene, ca. 1900; The Homestead, Albemarle, addition late 20th century; Homestead Style, Charlottesville, early 20th century; Home Track, (Home Tract), Crozet, ca. 1890, ca. 1994; Homestretch, Earlysville, addition ca. 1889; Hopewell, Browns Cove, 20th century; Hors de Ville, Charlottesville; Horseshoe Farm, Albemarle; Howard (Allan) Home, Howardsville; Howard- Jackson House, Charlottesville, ca. 1871-1875, 1906, 1965; Hudson (John) Home, Red Hill area, ca. 1828; Hudson-Smith House, Charlottesville, 1881; Humphrey-Abell House, (Hill and Dale; Frank Abell House), Albemarle, ca. 1880-1895; Humphries House, Charlottesville, razed; Hunt House, Albemarle, mid 19th century, early 20th century; Hunter's Hall, Albemarle, 1896; Hunting Box, Free Union/Earlysville; Huntin' Ridge Farm, Albemarle; Huyett-Bryan House, Charlottesville, 1901
  - Idylwood Studio, (William Edward Burgess Home), Scottsville 1993 (Box 11)
  - Ingleside, Keswick, 1885, 1917 1986 (Box 11)
  - Inn at Monticello, Albemarle, mid 19th century 1995 (Box 11)
  - Isole, Albemarle, ca. 1900 1996 (Box 11)
  - Ivy Creek Farm, (J. J. Woods Home), Ivy, mid 19th century, ca. 1939 1978 (Box 11)
  - Ivywood, Farmington, ca. 1936 1993 (Box 11)
  - Ix House, (Frank Ix Residence), Charlottesville, early 1930s, 1960 n.d. (Box 11)
  - "I" General 1968-1998 (Box 11)
    Indian Fields, Albemarle, late 18th century, burned 1854; Inglescress, Albemarle, 1986; Ingleridge Farm, Albemarle, 1941; Ingleside, North Garden; International Students House, Charlottesville, 1914; Ivory Log House, (Ivy Log House), Albemarle, ca. 1880; Ivy Cottage, Farmington area; Ivy Glen Farm, (Herbert Pettey House), Ivy, 20th century; Ivy Manor, (William W. Gilmer House; White Oaks), Albemarle, ca. 1845, burned ca. 1921
  - Jarman House, (Brugger House), Crozet, early 19th century 1976-1995 (Box 11)
  - Jarman-Cree House, (Walton House), Crozet, ca. 1860 1994-1995 (Box 11)
  - Jarman-Walker House, Jarmans Gap, ca. 1835 1976-1994 (Box 11)
  - Jeffries House, (Preddys Funeral Home), Charlottesville, 1858, 1934 1995 (Box 11)
  - Jeffries-Bruce House, (Martha K. Bruce Home; James M. Jeffries Home), Scottsville, ca. 1838 1978-1990 (Box 11)
  - Jones-Williams House, (Social Hall), Charlottesville, 1814 1974-1995 (Box 11)
  - Jordan-Morgan-Leitch-Haden House, Charlottesville, ca. 1806, ca. 1884, 1907 1978-1998 (Box 11)
  - Jumping Branch, Garth Road, Albemarle, 20th century 1995-1999 (Box 11)
  - "J" General 1978-1998 (Box 11)
    Jackson House, (Nanny Cox Jackson Home; William Wirt Law Office; City Hall site), razed 1968; Jacobs Run Farm, (John G. B. Crenshaw Farm), Earlysville, ca. 1850, ca. 1870; Jamestown (frame house from 1907 James Tercentenary, Crozet; J. N. Jarman House, (J. W. Gentry House), Crozet, 1908; John L. Jarman House, Charlottesville, 1892; East Jefferson Street House, Charlottesville, 1925; James L. Jessup House, Colthurst Farm, Charlottesville, 20th century; William Johnson, builder, Cismont, Stephen Jones Home, Charlottesville, 1925; Joseph-Batten House, (Batten Place), Batesville, ca. 1900
  - Keelona, (Redbrook), Carters Bridge, 1797, ca. 1850, 1940 1977-1995 (Box 11)
  - Keith House, (Daniel Keith Home, Nimmo Home), Charlottesville, ca. 1790, 1937 1983-1985 (Box 11)
  - Kelly House, (John Kelley House), 1828, mid 19th century, razed mid 20th century 1993 (Box 11)
  - Kenridge, (Colridge; Kappa Sigma Headquarters; site of original William Garth House), Albemarle, 1922, 1969 1965-1995 (Box 11)
  - Kenwood 1, (Fancy Hill), 1820s, mid 18th century, razed 20th century 1990-1997 (Box 11)
  - Kenwood 2, (site of Kenwood 1; Little White House; Frances Nash Home; Ellen Nash Foundation), 20th century, ca. 1938 1990-1998 (Box 11)
  - Keswick, (Turkey Hill; Dr. Thomas Walker House), Cash Corner, 1764, 1818, 1832 1980-1999 (Box 11)
  - Key House, Charlottesville, 1888 1993-1995 (Box 11)
  - Key West, Albemarle, ca. 1872 1978-1995 (Box 11)
  - Kinloch, (Margaret Patterson Home), Cismont, ca. 1764, razed, burned ca. 1839, May 1865, late 19th century, 1940s, 1995 1978-1995 (Box 11)
  - Kirgis House, Charlottesville, 1937 1993 (Box 11)
  - Kirklea, Ivy, ca. 1896, 1981 1990-1996 (Box 11)
  - "K" General 1990-1995 (Box 11)
    Kearsarge, (Robert Harris Woods House), Albemarle, 1926; Keene, house at, Albemarle, ca. 1900-1925; Kelly House, Kellytown, Charlottesville, 1868, 1870s; Kenmont, Farmington, 20th century; Keogh Home, North Garden, 1929; Kesmont, Cismont, ca.1950; The Keswick Estate, Keswick, 1997; Keswick Farm, Albemarle, 1810; Kilby/Joseph House, Albemarle, 1867; Kilham House, Farmington, 1941; King- Burgess House, Charlottesville, 1886; King-Runkle House, Charlottesville, 1891; Kyldeere Farm, Albemarle, 1981
  - Lanark, Albemarle, mid 19th century 1975-1995 (Box 12)
  - Landsdale Farm, Farmington Hunt, ca. 1810, late 20th century n.d. (Box 12)
  - Lands End, (Dr. Charles Minor Home; McLaughlin Home; Henry Crawford Home), ca. 1780, 1938, 1944-1947 1990 (Box 12)
  - Leaflands, (Olivet Presbyterian Church), Albemarle, 1920s 1989-1995 (Box 12)
  - Leathers House, Albemarle, ca. 1845, ca. 1905 1979 (Box 12)
  - Leathers-Snyders House, Charlottesville, 1891 1995 (Box 12)
  - Lego site, Albemarle, (Thomas Walker House; Jefferson Farm); early 19th century, 1894 1987 (Box 12)
  - Leitch House, (James S. Leitch House), Charlottesville, 1892, 1975 1992 (Box 12)
  - Lennox Farm, Green Mountain, early 18th century 1988-1995 (Box 12)
  - Lewis Level, (Stillwater Farm; Stockton Farm; Lone Oak; William Morris Home; Lady Blanca Rosenstiel Home), Albemarle, 1790, 1820s, 1962 1976-2000 (Box 12)
  - Lewis Mountain, (Kearny Mission; Society for Precious Blood; Thomas Campbell Home), Charlottesville, 1909, early 1920s 1937-1994 (Box 12)
  - Licking, (Lickin'; Bazille Brown Place), Browns Cove, ca. 1822, burned ca. 1940, razed 1984 1982-1995 (Box 12)
  - Limestone, Shadwell, (James/Andrew Monroe Home; George C. Blaetterman Home), 18th century, 1828, 1928 1976-1999 (Box 12)
  - Linden Farm, Crossroads, (John White Caroline Moore Home; Garnett White Home), ca. 1800, late 19th century, 1960s, 1991 1980-1996 (Box 12)
  - Linden (Old), Albemarle, (Nicholas Beary Home; David Branaman Home), late 18th century, ca. 1990 1980-1998 (Box 12)
  - Lion's Watch, (The Long C Farm; Henry A. Wise Home; Merrymore), Albemarle County, 1940-1941 1969 (Box 12)
  - Lipop House, Charlottesville, ca. 1836, late 19th century 1995 (Box 12)
  - Little Keswick, Keswick, (Keswick Orchard; Keswick Park; Elizabeth Wheeler Home), ca. 1870, mid 19th century n.d. (Box 12)
  - Little Mountain, (Locust Grove), Albemarle, ca. 1800, early 20th century, 1930s 1978-1995 (Box 12)
  - Lochlyn n.d. (Box 12)
  - Locust Farm, (Quintus Valentine Head & Mary Florence Feaganes Home), Free Union, early 19th century 1996 (Box 12)
  - Locust Grove, Charlottesville, 1840-1844, ca. 1890s, 1946-1947 1990 (Box 12)
  - Locust Hill, (Benjamin Johnson and Elizabeth Moorman Home), Howardsville, late 18th century 1991-1998 (Box 12)
  - Locust Hill, (Meriwether Lewis Birthplace), Ivy, 18th century, burned ca. 1837 1976-1995 (Box 12)
  - Logan, (Meriwether Lewis Walker House), Gordonsville, ca. 1836, 1840-1855 1979 (Box 12)
  - Log House, Rt. 750, Albemarle, mid 19th century 1996 (Box 12)
  - Logon, (Breitstein), Keswick Hunt Country, ca. 1870, 1930s 1977-1979 (Box 12)
  - Long Branch, (Samuel White Home), Ivy, early 19th century 1978-1998 (Box 12)
  - Longly, Albemarle, ca. 1850, ca. 1920 1993 (Box 12)
  - Longwood, Albemarle, 1765, ca. 1800, 1820 1974-1996 (Box 12)
  - Lyman Mansion, (Blue Ridge Sanitorium), Albemarle, 1876, 1922 1986 (Box 12)
  - Lynchburg Road houses, Albemarle n.d. (Box 12)
  - "L" General 1980-1995 (Box 12)